[SPEAKER_00]: So, I've been sent some questions and I thought I would try and answer them.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll see how many I get through.
[SPEAKER_00]: The first question is...
[SPEAKER_00]: I would love to learn more about the Buddha's words on solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know the saṅgha is one of the three jewels, but what about someone who isn't in an environment that includes people who follow the dhamma?
[SPEAKER_00]: Does avoiding others become then beneficial to the path of awakening?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, obviously, not hanging around people who are not interested in the dhamma,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to be beneficial if you want to actually learn about the dhamma and to hang around with people who are interested in that practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, it will encourage you and benefit you.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you can find people who actually know the dhamma, who have practiced it, then, obviously, that's going to be even better.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just because other people are interested in dhamma, doesn't necessarily mean that that is the best kind of people to be hanging around with, because they might be completely wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Their understanding of what dhamma is might be completely off.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you know, you've got to start somewhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: At least don't hang around people who have got absolutely no interest.
[SPEAKER_00]: No interest in trying to find out what the truth is.
[SPEAKER_00]: No interest in being authentic and honest with themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you can find a group that at least questions, each individual is questioning their own intentions, their own behaviors, that is a good person to be around and a good group to be around.
[SPEAKER_00]: But generally, you won't find that in groups.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might find an individual who is authentic.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you can recognize such an individual, try and make friends with him.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are many teachers out there, but just because someone's a teacher doesn't mean that they are... that they know what they're talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to find someone who is authentic, and you can only
[SPEAKER_00]: Do that with whatever authenticity you have for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you want to find people who are authentic, find people who are practicing well, you've got to start doing those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in that way, you will be able to recognize those qualities in others.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you're not doing those things for yourself, being authentic, practicing, keeping precepts, being honest with yourself, then you will not be able to recognize that in others.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as long as you're doing that, you'll find a group, you'll find others that will match that, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll be able to avoid those who do not match that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It'll be very clear to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, solitude is important, but solitude without authenticity,
[SPEAKER_00]: Without yourself making choices for yourself to not break the precept, to keep the precepts, to keep sense restraint, that is more important.
[SPEAKER_00]: Solitude will happen in and of itself later on, but you have to be authentic first, practice, keep the precepts, and naturally you will start to
[SPEAKER_00]: Choose directions in your life which move away from unwholesome people, unwholesome behavior, unwholesome contexts, unwholesome environments, and you will gravitate towards the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in a way, if you can be authentic yourself and practice wholeheartedly what the Buddha has instructed,
[SPEAKER_00]: You will be creating environments around you, so you don't really have to go that far to seek out a suitable environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: That environment is you, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your behavior is the environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to get away from an unwholesome environment?
[SPEAKER_00]: Start being wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Start acting wholesomely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Renounce all the bad things in your life and you would be in a suitable, secluded place, secluded from unbeneficial things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's got nothing to do with people necessarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's got to do with you and your choices that you're making in your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I hope that answers your question in terms of
[SPEAKER_00]: Solitude.